<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mrndq>

<gasan>

<title>Gasan</title>
<welcome>Welcome to Gasan!!!</welcome>

<gaspar>
<title>Gaspar Island</title>

<description><l1>Gaspar Island, known as the largest among the three islands in Gasan collectively called Tres Reyes Islands, got its name from the biblical three kings who presented gifts to the newborn Jesus in Bethlehem. Spanning approximately 108 hectares, the island was originally called "Laki," meaning big. Situated in Barangay Pinggan, Gasan, Marinduque, the Tres Reyes Islands, also referred to as the "Three Kings," form a chain of three islands located off the coast of Gasan.</l1>
<l2>This island is home to a significant archaeological site, particularly a cave where various artifacts have been discovered. Among the findings were burial jars exhibiting decorative patterns and shapes that align with the Kalanay complex style commonly found in Southeast Asia and South Vietnam from 500-400 BC to 1500 AD. In 1957, Beyer noted that specimens from this cave, collected by Marche, are still housed in the Trocadero Museum in Paris, as well as other French or Spanish museums. Some pieces have also made their way to the Smithsonian Institution. However, there have been no reports of re-examination of these artifacts or the cave site since then.</l2>
<l3>Presently, Gaspar Island is inhabited by a few families who rely on fishing for their livelihood. They also generate additional income by selling necklaces made from seashells to tourists. The island is part of a protected marine sanctuary. Its beach consists of a blend of white sand, crushed corals, and large boulders, complemented by steep cliffs and crystal-clear blue-green waters, making it an ideal location for swimming and snorkeling. Gaspar Island is a perfect spot for picnics and diving adventures in Marinduque.</l3></description>

<things>Explore the vibrant and pristine Gaspar Island Pinggan,Gasan, Marinduque where enjoyment starts from water activities like swimming, snorkeling and cliff diving, island hopping, and experiencing the breathtaking sunsets as well as booming island nightlife. It's no wonder the island attracts thousands of vacationers and couples who want to spend their time every year. Everyone wants a taste of the coveted beach/island life. There's always a fun tour or activity to do and somewhere to explore!</things>

<how>You can reach the islands in more or less half an hour by boat. You can organize a boat trip with the locals on the shore wherein the costs range from P1,500 and above.</how>
</gaspar>

<saintjoseph>
<title>St. Joseph Parish Church</title>

<description>The Parish of St. Joseph, the husband of Mary, can be found in Gasan, Marinduque. It is located on a hilltop, making the journey there a bit challenging, but the view is breathtaking as it provides a scenic overlook of the barangay and the sea. Throughout its history, the parish has undergone several relocations and renovations. The church boasts exquisite architecture both on the exterior and interior.
As you approach the church, the massive wooden doors adorned with intricate carvings of St. Joseph, Mother Mary, and the infant Jesus will immediately capture your attention. Stepping inside, your eyes will be drawn upwards to the ceiling, which resembles a golden fan. Upon closer inspection, you'll notice that the ceiling is adorned with depictions of our national leaf, the anahaw, intricately spread across the ceiling just above the rows of pews (long wooden benches where people sit in the church).
Furthermore, the church features colorful stained glass windows portraying scenes from the Bible. If you look beyond the altar, you'll catch sight of the Statue of Christ on the Cross, accompanied by numerous saints positioned on shelves with delicate lace-like carvings. The ceiling above the altar showcases beautiful paintings depicting St. Joseph and his acts of helping people.The feast day of St. Joseph, the spouse of Mary, is celebrated on May 19th in this parish.
</description>

<things>St.Joseph Parish Church is the best place to grasp the hardships of our lord Jesus Christ. It is dimly lit and quiet, housing a vast collection of authentic designs, and other religious items associated with the area. It is also the best place to repent of your sins and thank God for what he has given to us. The church has also its own cemetery where you can visit your passed loved ones.</things>

<how>You could either bring your own vehicle or ride a bus then take a Roro trip for at least 3-4 hours going to Balanacan post. The trip can costs at least 2,500 and up. From there, you can take a jeepney that travels to Gasan which will costs at alteast a hundred pesos.</how>
</saintjoseph>

<reyespark>
<title>Reyes Park</title>

<description>Reyes Park, a compact park situated in Barangay Dos, Gasan, Marinduque, offers a picturesque view of the Tres Reyes islands off the coast of Gasan. It also serves as Gasan's boardwalk, popularly known as the Gasan Baywalk, frequently hosting fairs and events. An exceptional feature of the park is a wooden suspension footbridge, the only one of its kind in Marinduque, which connects it to the adjacent Barangay Dili.
Reyes Park provides a refreshing and tranquil atmosphere. From the park's left side, you can admire the stunning sight of the three kings' islands, while the right side offers a beautiful view of Gasan's coastline. The late afternoon is the optimal time to visit as the temperature is milder, and the gentle sea breeze and the soothing sound of the waves create a serene ambiance. You'll be captivated by the cleanliness and unspoiled nature of the beach in this park. Additionally, a large passenger boat that travels to Pinamalayan, Mindoro, conveniently docks at this location.
</description>

<things>Reyes Park provides a refreshing and tranquil atmosphere. From the park's left side, you can admire the stunning sight of the three kings' islands, while the right side offers a beautiful view of Gasan's coastline. The late afternoon is the optimal time to visit as the temperature is milder, and the gentle sea breeze and the soothing sound of the waves create a serene ambiance. You'll be captivated by the cleanliness and unspoiled nature of the beach in this park. Additionally, a large passenger boat that travels to Pinamalayan, Mindoro, conveniently docks at this location.</things>

<how>You could either bring your own vehicle or ride a bus then take a Roro trip for at least 3-4 hours going to Balanacan post. The trip can cost at least 2,500 and up. From there, you can take a jeepney that travels to Gasan which will cost at least a hundred pesos.</how>
</reyespark>

</gasan>



<boac>

<title>Boac</title>
<welcome>Welcome to Boac!!!</welcome>

<boaccathedral>
<title>Boac Cathedral</title>

<description><l1>BOAC, Marinduque — The historic church located in the capital town of Boac, which is over 200 years old, serves not only as a cultural artifact but also as a significant symbol of the province's profound religious devotion.</l1>
<l2>Constructed in 1792, the Immaculate Conception Parish Church, commonly known as the Boac Cathedral, has stood as a "silent witness" to the history of Marinduque. It is one of the oldest heritage structures in the province, built around the 1590s, featuring earthquake baroque architecture. Positioned atop a hill, the cathedral is encompassed by imposing stone walls and fortifications. In earlier times, it served as a haven and stronghold for the locals. Within the enclosed compound lies the original site of the "Ina ng Biglang-awa" shrine.</l2>
<l3>In 1579, a Franciscan missionary named Fray Estevan Ortiz planted the first cross on Marinduque island. A year later, the first visita, called "Monserrat de Marinduque," now known as the municipality of Boac, was established, with Fray Alonzo Banol as its minister. In 1613, Miguel Garcia Serrano handed over the church's administration to the Archbishop of Manila, who subsequently entrusted the island to the Society of Jesus. The Jesuits assumed spiritual leadership of the island in 1621.</l3>
<l4>The townspeople regarded the cathedral not only as a place of worship but also as a sanctuary during attacks by Moro pirates. The locals would fervently pray to their patroness, Our Lady of the Immaculate Conception, seeking her protection against these invasions. The Moro pirates frequently assaulted the shores of Boac through the river mouth in Barangay Laylay. In one such attack, the invaders sought to kill numerous native defenders, but a powerful storm suddenly arose. The people witnessed a radiant apparition of a beautiful lady with outstretched arms, standing on the southern side of the church's fortress wall. This sight caused the invaders to flee. In honor of this event, the lady became known as "Ina ng Biglang Awa" as bestowed by the people.</l4>
<l5>In 1792, a marker on the church's front wall proclaimed, "naniniwala ang mga tao na siya ang nagligtas sa pagsalakay ng mga moro noong ika-18 dantaon" ("the people believe that she saved them from the Moro attack in the 18th century"). As an expression of dedication and gratitude to the Ina of Biglang Awa, the canonical coronation of the miraculous object of veneration took place in Boac on May 10, 1958, marking its 100th anniversary. Thousands of pilgrims from neighboring provinces in southern Luzon and Bicol attended the event. Her feast day falls on the 11th day of the month of November.</l5>
<l6>Today, the cathedral continues to stand as a prominent landmark of Marinduque province. Some of its interiors have been preserved, and it serves as the venue for the Moriones Festival. The people of the province actively preserve and protect the cathedral, ensuring that its legend is passed down through generations, instilling a sense of gratitude and a commitment to keeping history alive.</l6>
</description>

<things>The Boac Cathedral has been witness to various significant events in its long history. Inside the cathedral, the ambiance is peaceful with dim lighting, and it holds a diverse assortment of genuine designs and religious artifacts that are significant to the locality. The cathedral serves as an ideal venue for people to confess their sins and express gratitude to God for His blessings.</things>

<how>You could either bring your own vehicle or ride a bus then take a Roro trip for at least 3-4 hours going to Balanacan post. The trip can cost at least 2,500 and up. From there, you can take a jeepney that travels to Boac which will cost at least half of a hundred pesos.</how>
</boaccathedral>

<baliisseaofclouds>
<title>Baliis Sea of Clouds</title>

<description><l1>Every day, before dawn breaks, a multitude of individuals now gathers atop Mt. Baliis in Brgy. Bantay, Boac, depending on the weather conditions. Their purpose is to witness the breathtaking phenomenon known as the 'Sea of Clouds' and marvel at the magnificent scenery that unfolds before them, encompassing the forested hills and mountains below, where the once neglected barangays of Mahinhin and Hinapulan are nestled.</l1>
<l2>For the island's peace-loving residents, who have been fatigued, weary, and worn out by the burdens of the ongoing coronavirus pandemic, this newfound experience offers a much-needed respite, even if only for a few hours. It is something they had never encountered before in their beloved paradise island - the awe-inspiring 'Sea of Clouds.</l2>
<l3>Compelled by regular photographs capturing the ethereal beauty of the cloud formations, they feel a strong desire to be present in that moment, to feel closer to the Divine. After all, clouds have long been associated with the presence of God, and finding solace and tranquility in His midst.</l3>
<l4>Thanks to the construction of concrete roads, a venture that took decades to realize, it is now feasible to access this once-forgotten site by motorized vehicles.</l4></description>

<things>You with your family, friends or lover can take a picnic while watching the rise of the sun and as well as the clouds way down the valley. It's a perfect spot to take a sip of hot coffee or take a break from the stressing noise from a city. Since, the terrain is little sloppy but is cemented it is also perfect place to jog or cycle with your bikes.</things>

<how>You could either bring your own vehicle or ride a bus then take a Roro trip for at least 3-4 hours going to Balanacan post. The trip can cost at least 2,500 and up. From there, you can take a jeepney that travels to Boac which will cost at least half of a hundred pesos. Then, from boac you should have your own vehicle since it's far from the capital.</how>
</baliisseaofclouds>

</boac>



<stacruz>

<title>Sta. Cruz</title>
<welcome>Welcome to Sta. Cruz!!!</welcome>

<panuluyan>
<title>Panuluyan Farmstay</title>

<description><l1>The Panuluyan is not a resort, but rather a farmstay designed for those seeking a rural experience. Instead of luxurious amenities, guests can enjoy the genuine hospitality of the local community. It is managed not by individuals with degrees in Hotel and Restaurant Management, but by farmer families who are our partners in Masalukot.</l1></description>

<things>You with your family, friends or lover can take a picnic while watching the stars in the dark back sky. It's a perfect spot to take experience province life and be free from exhaustion. You can camp on the wide grassy spot, build a bonfire and make smores from a burnt mallows.</things>

<how>You could either bring your own vehicle or ride a bus then take a Roro trip for at least 3-4 hours going to Balanacan post. The trip can cost at least 2,500 and up. From there, you can take a jeepney that travels to Boac which will cost at least half of a hundred pesos. Then, from boac you should have your own vehicle since it's far from the capital.</how>
</panuluyan>

<maniwaya>
<title>Maniwaya Island</title>

<description><l1>Maniwaya Island, situated in Santa Cruz, Marinduque, is a highly sought-after destination within the province. Positioned between Polo Island and Mompong Island, it captivates visitors with its pristine white sand beaches.</l1>
<l2>A sandbar is also the one that captives the heart of tourists which  typically requires a minimum entrance fee of PhP 20, although the exact amount may vary depending on your chosen accommodation on the island. For an additional fee, visitors can also opt to camp or rent a cottage at one of the island's resorts.</l2>
<l3>Due to its popularity as a tourist destination, Maniwaya Island tends to attract crowds during weekends and holidays. To experience a more serene environment, it is advisable to plan your visit on weekdays. As an outdoor destination, the ideal time to explore Maniwaya Island is during the dry season, which generally spans from December to May.</l3></description>

<things>Both the southwest and northeast sides of Maniwaya Island boast an extensive shoreline spanning approximately one kilometer. On the southwest side, visitors can find affordable accommodations and engage in water activities such as snorkeling and free diving. Meanwhile, the northeast side is home to the renowned Palad Sandbar, offering breathtaking views of sunrise and sunset.
While exploring Maniwaya Island, locals often recommend venturing to nearby attractions like the Palad Sandbar. This enchanting stretch of crushed coral sands emerges during low tide and entices snorkelers with its stunning underwater coral garden. </things>

<how>To reach Maniwaya Island in Marinduque, there are two primary transportation options available. If you prefer air travel, you can book a flight from Manila to Marinduque's airport in Gasan. Upon arrival, you will need to proceed to Sta Cruz and then to Buyabod Port. The journey covers approximately 47 kilometers and takes approximately one and a half hours. From Buyabod Port, you can board a boat that will take you to Maniwaya Island.Alternatively, you can choose to travel by land from Manila. Begin by making your way to Lucena Grand Terminal in Quezon province, which can be reached by bus. From there, you can take either a bus or a van to General Luna Port. At the port, you can find a passenger boat that will transport you to Maniwaya Island. It is important to check the boat schedule in advance, as there is usually only one departure per day for the island. Depending on the specific route you take, the land journey from Manila to Maniwaya Island can take up to seven hours.</how>
</maniwaya>

<hakupan>
<title>Hakupan Island</title>

<description><l1>Hakupan Island is a 4.6 hectares islet of the northern part of Marinduque. A beautiful site that has such clear water and a long stretch of the sandbar.  There is also a spot where you can go snorkeling which they are currently re-building after most parts were destroyed because of illegal fishing.</l1></description>

<things>It is one of the famous sweet spot of Botilao locals for swimming and snorkeling.</things>

</hakupan>

</stacruz>



<mogpog>

<title>Mogpog</title>
<welcome>Welcome to Mogpog!!!</welcome>

<paadjao>
<title>Paadjao Falls</title>

<description><l1>While Marinduque is famous for its scenic beaches, there is one enchanting waterfall that stands out from the rest of the Mogpog Marinduque tourist spots, the Paadjao Falls. Situated in Mogpog municipality, the Paadjao Falls is accessible via a 10-minute trek from the highway, which is only 5.5KM away.</l1>
<l2>The concealed waterfall delicately descends from a 15-foot rocky cliff, creating a tranquil cascade that empties into a 6-foot deep basin with refreshing jade-green waters. Serenely tucked beneath the shade of lush greenery and towering trees, it provides a profound sense of closeness to the natural world. The falls are surrounded by large, rugged rocks, so caution is advised when navigating the river and waterfall.</l2>
<l3>Paadjao Falls is connected to the downstream section of the Mogpog River, offering an ideal location for picnics and the opportunity to set up tents for camping. Alongside Paadjao Falls, Marinduque boasts other lesser-known waterfalls, including Norada Falls, Kawa Kawa Falls, and Bulusukan Falls.</l3></description>

<things>It is an ideal place for picnicking or camping. Paadjao Falls is an ideal place for family picnics and camping.</things>

</paadjao>

<luzondatum>
<title>Luzon Datum</title>

<description><l1>Marinduque, known as the "Heart of the Philippines," is a province located in the Southern Tagalog Region. Remarkably, this heart-shaped island also happens to be the geographical center of the entire archipelago, and its significance is marked by a stone marker. Referred to as the Luzon Datum of 1911 or Station Balanacan, this marker is situated atop a hill locally known as Mataas na Bundok or Mt. Mataas in Barangay Hinanggayon, Mogpog. It serves as the primary geodetic reference point for all geological surveys in the Philippines, making it the origin from which all maps and surveys in the country are based.</l1></description>


<how>To reach this site, one must take a ride to Barangay Hinanggayon in Mogpog, which can be a bumpy and rough journey. Upon arrival in Barangay Hinanggayon, it is advisable to proceed to the Barangay Hall to register and pay respects to the Barangay officials. From there, you have the option to either trek up to the top of the datum or, if you have a vehicle, drive up to the designated parking area. Keep in mind that the terrain can be steep and uneven. Simply follow the straight path until you reach a set of concrete stairs leading to the Luzon Datum. While the trek may be tiring, it is a truly worthwhile experience.</how>
</luzondatum>

<balanacancove>
<title>Balanacan Cove</title>

<description><l1>This secluded cove holds great historical significance in Marinduque and is considered one of the province's most idyllic locations. It was chosen by the Spanish Admiralty as a construction and repair facility for the Spanish navy, where notable vessels such as the galleon "San Juan de Bautista" and the almirante "San Marcos" were built. During the final stages of World War II, on November 25, 1944, two out of the four Imperial Japanese Navy warships hiding in the cove were sunk by American dive bombers from the USS Intrepid, resulting in the loss of thousands of Japanese lives. Today, the remains of these two sunken Japanese ships rest beneath 140 feet of water, providing advanced wreck divers with an opportunity for exploration.</l1>
<l2>Balanacan now serves as the main gateway to the province, catering to both commuter traffic and commerce. The surrounding area is dotted with small islets that are perfect for activities such as snorkeling, scuba diving, and picnics.Situated near the boundary of Brgy. Ino, the Balanacan View Deck and Bacud Hill offer breathtaking views. The view deck has been reconstructed into a two-story concrete structure, providing visitors with a 270-degree panoramic view of the northwestern portion of Mogpog. Overlooking the north side of the area, Bacud Hill was previously a port facility for the Goldstar Mining Corporation, operating as an iron ore mine port during the pre-war and post-war periods until the 1950s. Currently, an access road leads to an unfinished concrete structure on Bacud Hill, which is intended to serve as a roofdeck open view area. There are plans to designate this site as a World War II Memorial Site to honor both the victors and the vanquished of the war, as well as to commemorate the air and naval battle that took place in the waters surrounding the hill.</l2></description>

</balanacancove>

</mogpog>



<torrijos>
<title>Torrijos</title>
<welcome>Welcome to Torrijos!!!</welcome>

<poctoy>
<title>Poctoy White Beach</title>

<description><l1>Poctoy White Beach, located in the coastal municipality of Torrijos, is a renowned destination in Marinduque. This expansive shoreline boasts a long stretch of fine white sand, fringed by swaying palm trees. The beach is embraced by clear, sparkling waters that offer an ideal setting for activities like swimming and kayaking. Along the beach, there are beachfront huts and cottages equipped with chairs and tables, providing a perfect spot to relax and enjoy leisurely afternoons.</l1>

<l2>Beneath the crystalline waters, scuba divers are treated to a captivating sight. The Poctoy Underwater Museum showcases impressive Moryon monuments, which symbolize the iconic Moriones festival celebrated by the people of Marinduque during Holy Week.</l2>

<l3>Beyond its reputation as a picturesque beach, Poctoy White Beach is emerging as one of the must-visit tourist spots in Torrijos, Marinduque. Its pristine shores and breathtaking sunset views that paint the horizon attract both local and international travelers, making it a popular destination year after year.</l3></description>

<things>Picnics, Snorkeling, Crystal kayak, and Camping.</things>

</poctoy>

</torrijos>



<buenavista>

<title>Buenavista</title>
<welcome>Welcome to Buenavista!!!</welcome>

<haynon>
<title>Haynon Hills</title>

<description>Situated at the base of the western slopes of the Balagbag Mountain Range, these rolling hills have served as grazing grounds and provide a tranquil vista of various elevations and undulating terrain covered in scattered patches of grass. During the dry summer months, the grasslands take on a brown hue, earning them the nickname "Chocolate Hills of Haynon," while they turn lush green in the rainy season. Today, this area has become a popular destination for hikers, mountain bikers, and casual visitors alike. </description>

<things>This is the best place to hike, bike, unwind and shout out all your feelings.</things>

<how>To access this location, take a barangay road that veers to the left before reaching the Malbog Sulfur Springs. </how>
</haynon>

<malindig>
<title>Mt. Malindig</title>

<description>Mount Malindig, located on the island of Marinduque in the Philippines, is a sizable stratovolcano with potential volcanic activity. It stands as the largest mountain on Marinduque and is highly regarded as a popular destination for climbers and hikers, renowned for its exceptional environmental diversity. The mountain is teeming with various species of wild orchids and other endemic wildlife, making it a haven for biodiversity. In recognition of its elevation exceeding 1,000 meters (3,300 ft) above sea level, it has been designated as a protected area by law. Comprising three peaks, the trek, and ascent to the summit are generally considered to be of easy to moderate difficulty. Beyond the Radio Station base, the trail transforms into a mossy and densely forested path, often shrouded in regular foggy conditions. Additionally, the Buenavista community utilizes the mountain's lower regions as grazing grounds for cattle.</description>

<things>The ascent of Malindig proved to be the most challenging experience. The intense heat, compounded by the scarcity of trees along the trail, made it particularly demanding. The path to the summit stretched ahead in an almost unbroken line, with minimal respite from the sun's relentless rays. Despite completing the journey to the campsite in under two hours, I found myself needing frequent breaks along the way.
Upon reaching the campsite, a noticeable drop in temperature accompanied the setting sun, signaling the arrival of a thick blanket of fog that enveloped the mountain. The mist grew so dense that visibility was limited to a mere five meters. Failing to bring adequate warmth proved to be a grave oversight.</things>

</malindig>

<villaroca>
<title></title>

<description></description>

<things></things>

<how></how>
</villaroca>

<wildlife>
<title>Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary</title>

<description>The Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary encompasses an expansive woodland area of approximately 9,000 hectares in Central Marinduque. This natural habitat serves as a haven for a diverse array of plant and animal species, including the endangered Rufous Hornbill (Rufous hydrocorax), the majestic giant cloud pig (Phloeomys pallidus), as well as various indigenous butterflies, reptiles, insects, and birds.
Recognizing the remarkable abundance of flora and fauna in this region, the Marinduque Wildlife Sanctuary has been designated as one of the few protected areas in the Philippines. Since travelers will have to go on a trek to reach this sanctuary, it's best to go on a trip here during the local dry season (December to May). </description>

<things>Be refreshed by the extensive green farm where different animals are free to do whatever they want. You can feed some of them with the veggies or grasses just like what they do in zoo.</things>

<how>To reach the sanctuary, visitors embark on a trek that typically lasts around two hours, depending on individual pace. Along the trail, you will be greeted by scenic rolling hills, captivating panoramic views, and occasional glimpses of enchanting small waterfalls.</how>
</wildlife>

</buenavista>

</mrndq>